A Guide to the James Hunter Court Papers, 1795-1797
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
James Hunter Court Papers, 1795-1797
The Library of Virginia
23762b
74 leaves, negative photostats
Estate of James Hunter
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying, 21 December 1951, by Leon M. Bazile, Virginia Fifteenth Circuit Court.
Biographical Information
James Hunter was born in 1721 in Scotland. Becoming involved in his family's mercantile business, Hunter made trips to Virginia for business before permanently settling in Stafford County, Virginia. Hunter became a successful businessman and landowner, and was the largest single slave owner in Stafford County. Hunter operated an iron-works along the Rappahannock River. During the Revolution, he produced arms and supplies for the American cause. Never married, Hunter died in November 1784.
Scope and Content
Court papers, 1795-1798, in the suit of James Hunter's executors vs. William Richards, all of Stafford County, Virginia, in a suit before the Fredericksburg District Court concerning the right to erect a water grist mill along the Rappahannock River.
Contents List
- Order, October 1795, from the Stafford County Court allowing Adam Hunter and Patrick Home, executors of James Hunter, to erect a grist mill.
- Record on appeal, 1795-1797, in the case of Hunter's executors vs. Richards.
- Report, 1797, on exceptions to the construction of the mill by Hunter and Home.
- Bond, 16 October 1797, from Patrick Home and Charles Croughton to William Richards for construction of a grist mill
- Bond, 16 October 1797, from Patrick Home and Charles Croughton to William Richards for construction of a grist mill.
- Exhibits consisting of transcripts of deeds, grants, and wills.
  - Land grant, 12 December 1690, for 1260 acres to Thomas Vicaris.
  - Deed, recorded 4 November 1768 in General Court, for land in King George County, Virginia, from John Dixon of Gloucester County, Virginia, to James Hunter of King George County
  - Land grant, 2 June 1703, for 1260 acres to Martha Vicaris.
  - Deeds of lease and release, recorded 3 February 1748, for 900 acres in King George County from Martha Todd of King and Queen County, Virginia, to John Dixon of Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Deed, recorded 4 April 1796 in King George County, for 300 acres in King George County from John Dixon to John Richards of King George County.
  - Will, recorded 5 December 1758 in Prerogative Court of Canterbury, of John Dixon of Bristol, England.
  - Will, recorded March 1785 in Stafford County, of John Richards.
  - Deed, recorded 17 April 1784 in General Court, for 1 acre in Stafford County from Francis Thornton of Spotsylvania County, Virginia, to James Hunter of Stafford County.
  - Will, recorded December 1784 in Stafford County, of James Hunter
  - Deed, recorded 2 October 1766, for 7 acres in King George County, from John Dixon of Gloucester County to James Hunter of King George County.
  - Survey, 24-28 December 1793, of lands in Stafford County belonging to William Richards by James Leach.
  - Plat, no date, of unidentified lands bordering the Potomac River.